Finding Aid for School of Natural Resources and Environment (University of Michigan) Records 1903-2012.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Natural Resources and Environment (University of Michigan) records
1903-2012
University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources and Environment.
Academic unit of the University of Michigan established in 1903 as the Department of Forestry. Records include dean's administrative files, correspondence, minutes, reports and photographs documenting the administration of the school as well as classroom and field activities.
87308 Bimu C241 2 BImu Out
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
75 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
989 MB
The records were transferred by the School of Natural Resources and Environment (Donor No. 1887 ) in several accessions.
The School of Natural Resources and Environment records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation and student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from the date of creation.
In addition, records of the School added to the record group after January 1, 2001 are restricted for twenty years from date of accession in accordance with the university's policy on the records of Executive Officers, Deans, Directors and their support offices. Records in this category are identified with an "ER restricted" note.
The School of Natural Resources and Environment record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 51-53
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 51-53
Executive Records -- Box 56--70
The School of Natural Resources (SNR) was established in 1927 but forestry courses had been offered at the University of Michigan as early as 1881. It was the first university in the United States to offer regular course work in forestry. The first forestry course was given in 1881 by Professor Morgan Volney Spalding in the School of Political Science. This forestry offering lapsed after four years, however.
In 1901, at the instigation of Spalding and Charles W. Garfield of Grand Rapids, the Board of Regents voted to renew the forestry program. Charles Albert Davis was appointed special instructor in forestry and courses were offered in 1902. The following year a separate Forestry Department, headed by Filibert Roth, was created in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A). The department offered a combined undergraduate and graduate program that included four years of the usual course work for the B.A. with forestry electives, and one year of graduate study.
Under Roth's direction the curriculum and the faculty expanded to keep pace with developments in the forestry profession. The University of Michigan became one of the best known forestry schools. Professor Roth retired in 1923. The naming of a successor was delayed as University President Burton used the occasion of Roth's retirement to undertake a reevaluation of the forestry program.
In 1926 the Regents voted approval for an expanded forestry program. This led to the creation of an independent School of Forestry and Conservation in 1927. Samuel Trask Dana was named the school's first dean. Dana immediately began to recruit new faculty and develop a more comprehensive curriculum. Enrollment, which had declined due to the uncertainty following Roth's retirement and the impact of the depression, began to grow steadily after 1931. Spurred by the work of the Civilian Conservation Corps and other government conservation activity, enrollment reached 187 full-time students in 1939/40. With the onset of World War II, the number of students dropped precipitously only to be followed by a postwar boom in enrollment.
In 1949 a committee of four noted conservationists was engaged to consider a reorganization of the school in light of developments in the forestry and conservation professions. The committee report was received favorably, but Dean Dana had prepared his own more sweeping proposal for reorganization. His plan called for creation of an expanded School of Natural Resources which would offer degrees in regional planning and general conservation in addition to the traditional training programs in forestry, wood technology, wildlife management, and fisheries management.
The School of Natural Resources originally had been organized into five departments: Forestry, Wood Technology, Fisheries Management, Wildlife Management, and Conservation. The first three departments were carried over from the old Department of Forestry. Fisheries Management had been located in the Zoology Department of LS&A. As its work had become more applied, it was deemed appropriate to shift the fisheries program to the School of Natural Resources.
The Conservation Department developed from a $100,000 grant from the Charles Lathrop Pack Foundation for the purpose of training students in the entire field of conservation. Noted ecologist Stanley A. Cain was named the first Pack Professor of Conservation in 1950. The Conservation Department offered a number of interdisciplinary programs including natural resources economics with the Economics Department and environmental planning and water resources with the School of Public Health. By the mid-1960s conservation had become the largest SNR department. To better reflect its expanded curriculum, the Conservation Department's name was changed to Resource Planning and Conservation in 1969.
While the Conservation Department was growing, other departments experienced little or no growth, prompting some significant reorganization of the school. The Wood Technology Department was phased out in 1964 and its faculty transferred to Forestry. In 1965 the Fisheries and Wildlife Management Departments were administratively combined but separate curriculums were maintained.
Also in 1965, SNR acquired a new department with the transfer of Landscape Architecture from the College of Architecture and Design. During this period SNR instituted a naturalist curriculum and expanded its offerings in forest recreation. The latter development resulted in the endowing of the Samuel T. Dana Professorship of Outdoor Recreation.
The School of Natural Resources has also been host to several interdepartmental projects. These include the Remote Sensing of the Environment Program, the Environmental Simulation Laboratory, and the Sea Grant Program.
In 1970 the university undertook a broad review of its programs relating to environmental education and the management and development of natural resources. A university-wide committee headed by Vice President Stephen Spurr recommended that the university establish a College of Environmental Studies of which SNR would be a part. The College of Environmental Studies was not established but SNR did revise its structure and curriculum along the lines recommended by the Spurr committee. The existing SNR departments were abolished and programs were to be offered in six areas: Systems Management; Fisheries, Forestry, and Wildlife; Resource Ecology; Resource Policy and Administration; Environmental Education; and Landscape Architecture.
Over the years SNR has acquired or managed several forest properties for educational and scientific purposes. These have included the Eberwhite Woods in west Ann Arbor, the Saginaw Forest property further west of Ann Arbor on Liberty Road, the Stinchfield Woods property near Dexter, the Ringwood tract near Saginaw, and Camp Filibert Roth in Iron County.
As noted above, Samuel Trask Dana was named the first dean of SNR in 1927. He guided the school for twenty-three years until his retirement in 1950. He remained an active presence in the school as emeritus dean. Dana selected his own successor, Stanley G. Fontanna. Formerly deputy director of the State of Michigan Department of Conservation, Fontanna held the deanship from 1951 to 1962. He was succeeded by Stephen H. Spurr, professor of silviculture. Spurr served through 1965 when he was appointed dean of the university's Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.
Kenneth P. Davis, professor of forest management, was appointed interim dean for 1965/66. Dr. Keith Arnold of the U.S. Forest Service served as dean for three years, 1967-1969. Arnold was succeeded by James T. McFadden, chairman of the school's Department of Fisheries and Wildlife Management. McFadden was the first non-forester to be named dean and served as dean until 1974.
William J. Johnson, chairman of the school's Landscape Architecture program, was selected to succeed McFadden. When Johnson stepped down as dean in 1983 to return to academics, he was succeeded by James E. Crowfoot. Confronted with budget reductions and a review by the University of Michigan, Crowfoot provided SNR with the necessary leadership during an intense period of scrutiny. Crowfoot stepped down as dean in December 1990 to chair the Resource, Policy and Behavior concentration and left the University of Michigan in 1994 to assume the presidency of Antioch College. In addition to his responsibilities as dean, Crowfoot was co-founder of the Program in Conflict Management Alternatives. An advocate of the democratic management of organizations, he developed a new curriculum emphasis in environmental dispute resolution.
Following Crowfoot's resignation Harrison Morton was appointed interim dean of the school until the appointment of Garry D. Brewer in 1992. Among Brewer's first achievements was implementing a name change for the School of Natural Resources. During the July 1992 meeting the University of Michigan Board of Regents approved a name change to the School of Natural Resources and Environment (SNRE). The name changes was designed to reflect the expanding scope of the school. Brewer left the deanship in 1995 and Paul Webb was appointed interim dean. Daniel A. Mazmanian, was appointed dean in June 1996.
Leadership of the School of Natural Resources and Environment and its Predecessors
Chairman of the Department of Forestry
1903-1923 Filibert Roth
1923-1927 Leigh J. Young (acting)
1927 Robert Craig, Jr. (acting)
Dean of the School of Forestry and Conservation
1927-1950 Samuel Trask Dana
Deans of the School of Natural Resources
1950/1951 Samuel Trask Dana
1951-1962 Stanley George Fontanna
1962-1965 Stephen H. Spurr
1965-1966 Kenneth Davis (Interim)
1967-1969 Keith Arnold
1970-1974 James T. McFadden
1974-1975 Charles Olson (Interim)
1975-1983 William J. Johnson
1983-1990 James Crowfoot
1991-1992 Harrison Morton (Interim)
School of Natural Resources and Environment
1992-1995 Garry D. Brewer
1995 Paul Webb (Interim)
1996-2000 Daniel A. Mazmanian
2000-2001 Barry Rabe (Interim)
2001- Rosina M. Bierbaum
The School of Natural Resources records comprise 54 linear feet and span a wide range of years from 1903 to 1994. The records document the internal activities of the school, both administrative and academic; the role of the school as a unit of the University of Michigan; and curricular changes and the development of new academic programs over the years.
Subjects:
Baxter, Dow Vawter, 1898-1965.; College publications.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Ecology--Study and teaching.; Marquis, Stewart.; Tealdi, Aubrey.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Landscape Architecture.; University of Michigan. Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; Whittemore, Harlow Olin, 1889-1986.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Belle Isle (Detroit, Mich.); Benzie County (Mich.); Cadillac (Mich.); Clinton River (Mich.); Cobbs & Mitchell.; Eberwhite Woods (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Fire fighters--Michigan.; Forest fires--Michigan.; Forestry.; Grand Traverse County (Mich.); Hartland (Mich.); Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Isle Royale (Mich.); Johannesburg (Mich.); Leelanau County (Mich.); Ludington State Park (Mich.); Lumber industry.; Michigan, Northern.; Pictured Rocks (Mich.); Rangers--Michigan.; Saginaw Forest (Mich.); Slides.; Stinchfield Woods (Mich.); Tahquamenon River (Mich.); University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; University of Michigan. Forestry Club.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources--Faculty.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Woodlawn Cemetery (Detroit, Mich.); Upper Falls (Luce County, Mich.); Lower Falls (Chippewa County, Mich.); Nevue, Wilfred, 1886-
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- Faculty Meetings, 1927-1991
  The Faculty Meetings series is arranged chronologically by academic year and spans the period from 1927/28 through 1990/91. There are yearly indexes through academic year 1940/41. These meeting materials represent the main record of the school's governing body
  - 1927/1928-1964/1965, 30 folders (Box 1)
  - 1965/1966-1978/1979, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - 1979/1980-December 1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - January 1983-December 1988, 12 folders (Box 19)
  - January 1989-April 1991, 3 folders (Box 20)
- Executive Committee Meetings, 1971-1991
  The Executive Committee Meetings series (.6 linear ft.) documents the functions and deliberations of the core administrative body of SNR. Its records consist of minutes, discussion papers, and memoranda from the years 1971 to 1990/91.
  - February 1971-1972/1973 (Box 3)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - 1976-1977, 1 volumes; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1977-1978, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1978/79-1979/80, 1 volumes; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - 1980/81 (Box 18)
  - 1981/82 (Box 18)
  - 1982/83 (Box 18)
  - 1983/84 (Box 18)
  - 1984/85, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1985/86, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1986/87, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1987/88, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1988/89, 5 folders
    - Folders 1-3 (Box 18)
    - Folders 4-5 (Box 19)
  - 1989/90 (Box 19)
    (Fall only)
  - 1990/91 (scattered dates) (Box 19)
- Dean's Correspondence Files, 1964-1990
  The series of Dean's Correspondence Files consists of copies of the dean's outgoing correspondence. The Correspondence is organized in two subseries: Chronological and Memoranda to Faculty. The chronological files are arranged by academic year from 1964/65 to 1989/90, and within each year are ordered alphabetically. The correspondence covers a range of subjects from routine administrative matters to policy issues.
  - Chronological
    - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1967/1968-1968/1969, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - 1969-1970, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1971-1972, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1972-1973, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1973/74, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - 1974/75 (Box 34)
    - 1975/76-1981/82, 7 volumes (Box 35)
    - 1982/83, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - 1983/84, 3 folders (Box 36)
    - 1984/85, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - 1985/86 (Box 36)
    - 1986/87, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - 1987/88, 3 folders
      - Folder 1 (Box 36)
      - Folders 2-3 (Box 37)
    - 1988/89, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - 1989/90, 3 folders (Box 38)
    - 1990-1993, 17 folders (Box 63)
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2032 ]
    - 1993-1996, 18 folders (Box 64)
    - 2005-2007 (Box 64)
  - Memoranda to Faculty, 1978-1983; 3 folders (Box 38)
    - 1978-1983, 3 folders (Box 38)
  - Alphabetical
    - 1992-1996, 8 folders (Box 65)
  - Personal
    - 1992, 4 folders (Box 66)
- General Topical Files, 1913-1990
  The General Topical Files series consists for the most part of historical files covering a range of topics. The series is composed of two subseries reflecting separate, but chronologically overlapping alphabetically arranged files. Of special interest is the correspondence with alumni serving in World War II ("Alumni in WW II, Correspondence from and Newspaper Clippings about"), and Dean Dana's correspondence with various people regarding the history of the lumber industry in Michigan and lumberjack lore ("History of Lumber Industry in Michigan"). Also included in this small series are historical statistics regarding curriculum offerings, degrees conferred, and student dissertation topics.
  - 1913-1980
    - Alumni
      - Alumni in WWII, Correspondence from and Clippings, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
      - Circular Letter to Alumni, 1913 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence with Aldo Leopold re: Game Management, 1928-1930 (Box 4)
    - Courses and Curricula
      - General, 1927-1951 (Box 4)
        (includes degrees conferred)
      - Course Approvals, 1950-1958; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Faculty
      - Faculty Bylaws, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
      - Faculty Code, 1973-1978 (Box 4)
      - Faculty Policy Decisions, A Record of, 1927-1953 (Box 4)
    - History of Lumber Industry in Michigan (S.T. Dana's correspondence regarding), 1932-1935; 1941 (Box 4)
    - Students
      - General (includes dissertation topics), 1927-1952 (Box 4)
      - Enrollment Statistics
        - Fall 1905-Spring 1927 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1927-Spring 1940 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1940-Spring 1947 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1947-Spring 1950 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1950-Spring 1952 (Box 4)
    - Statement of Aims and Policies of School of Forestry and Conservation (letter to President Little), 1927 (Box 4)
  - 1928-1990
    The 1928-1990 subseries of the General Topical Files (6.2 linear ft., received in the 1989-1991 accessions) primarily address issues internal to the School of Natural Resources. Numerous committees and task forces are represented in this series, among them the Academic Affairs Committee and the Promotion and Tenure Committee. Topics relating to academic endeavors and curriculum development include "Problem Centered Laboratory Network (PCLN)" and "Specialization Coordinators." Other significant material in this series are the papers of former faculty member Dow V. Baxter (under "Faculty"), materials dating from the 1940s to the 1980s about land owned and/or utilized by the school ("Properties of SNR" also see Box 54 for additional material on SNR properties), and a review of the Wildland Management Center. The folders "Goals and Objectives" provide insight on the school's future direction.
    - Academic Affairs Committee (SNR), 1984/85-1989/90
      - 1984/85, 2 folders (Box 51)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2060 ]
      - 1985/86, 2 folders (Box 52)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2061 ]
      - 1986/87, 2 folders (Box 52)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2062 ]
      - 1987/88, 2 folders (Box 52)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2063 ]
      - 1988/89, 2 folders (Box 52)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2064 ]
      - 1989/90, 2 folders (Box 52)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2065 ]
    - Academic Programs, Office for (SNR)
      - General
        - 1988/89 (Box 20)
        - 1989/90 (Box 20)
      - Surveys of Employers, 1990 (Box 20)
    - Administrative Issues, 1978-1988 (Box 20)
    - Admissions, Office of (UM), 1984-1988 (Box 20)
    - Associate Dean Search, 1983 (Box 52)
    - Bassett, John (Associate Dean)
      - Correspondence, 1977-1984 (Box 20)
      - Curricula and Teaching Loads of Faculty, 1984-1985 (Box 20)
      - Memoranda to Dean and Faculty, 1983-1984 (Box 20)
    - Budget Requests
      - 1988/89 (Box 20)
      - 1989/90 (Box 20)
    - Committee Objectives, 1984-1987 (Box 20)
    - Concentration Chairs Meetings, 1988/89 (Box 20)
    - Conservation Biology and Ecosystem Management and Natural Resources Organizational Management Programs, Task Force on, 1989-1990 (Box 20)
    - Continuing Education/Midcareer Program, 1983-1984 (Box 20)
    - Cooperative Management Areas: Ottawa National Forest (Ironwood, MI), 1942-1961; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Dana Society, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Diversity, Committee on, 1988; 1989 (Box 21)
    - Enrollment Statistics, 1973/74-1980/81; 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Environmental Advocacy Concentration, undated
    - Faculty
      - Allen, Shirley Walter, 1956-1958 (Box 21)
      - Baxter, Dow V.
        - Correspondence, 1928-1965; 2 folders (Box 21)
        - Memorial Service and Disposition of Materials, 1966 (Box 21)
        - Writings, 1954-1966 (Box 21)
      - Bylaws, 1980-1984 (Box 21)
      - Faculty Instruction Records, 1960/61-1961/62 (Box 21)
      - Faculty Retreat, January 1979 (Box 21)
      - Promotions, 1974-1978
        - 1974/75 (Box 52)
        - 1975/76 (Box 52)
        - 1976/77 (Box 52)
        - 1977/78 (Box 52)
      - Regional Planning Faculty Award, 1977-1984 (Box 21)
      - Staffing Needs, 1986 (Box 21)
    - Forestry, 1986-1988 (Box 21)
    - Geographic Information Systems, 1987-1990 (Box 21)
    - Goals and Objectives, 1984/85-1987/88; 1990; 3 folders (Box 21)
      (includes Administrative Team Retreat)
    - Golden Lake Area, Permanent Sample Plots Reports, 1945; 1950 (Box 22)
    - Governance and Organization, 1984 (Box 22)
    - Graduate Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 22)
    - Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences, Center for
      - General, 1987-1989 (Box 22)
      - Appointments, 1988-1989 (Box 52)
        [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2019 ]
      - Director Search, 1989 (Box 52)
    - Landscape Architecture, 1984-1990 (Box 22)
    - Microcomputer Group Meetings, 1986-1987 (Box 22)
    - Natural Resource Economics Program, 1978-1981 (Box 22)
    - "New Ground" Symposia, 1980 (Box 22)
      (includes photos and color slides)
    - Problem Centered Laboratory Network (PCLN)
      - General, 1976-1978 (Box 22)
      - Case Studies
        - General, 1977-1978 (Box 22)
        - Case Study Ad Hoc Team, 1977 (Box 22)
        - Case Study Workshops, 1977-1978 (Box 22)
        - Dolph Park (includes photos from 1960s), 1978 (Box 22)
        - Pigeon River, 1974-1978 (Box 22)
      - Committee Meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 22)
      - Diagrams and Charts, 1976 (Box 22)
      - Handwritten Notes, undated (Box 22)
      - Reports
        - "A Special Report on a Proposed PCLN,", 1977 (Box 22)
        - Untitled, November 1977 (Box 22)
    - Promotion and Tenure Committee
      - General, 1977-1988; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Faculty Evaluation, 1980-1984 (Box 53)
    - Promotion Process, 1973-1978 (Box 22)
    - Properties of SNR
      - General, 1954-1982 (Box 23)
      - Annual Reports, 1950/51-1956/57; 1962/63; 1965/66; 1966/67; 1975/76-1981/82 (Box 23)
      - Applications for SNR Property Use, 1987-1988 (Box 23)
      - Camp Filibert Roth
        - General (includes photo), 1963-1978; 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Annual Reports, 1960; 1962-1968 (Box 23)
        - Camp Committee, 1960; 1963; 1970; 1976-1977 (Box 23)
        - Evaluation, 1972 (Box 23)
        - Reports on Timber Estimates and Permanent Sample Plots, 1945-1946 (Box 23)
      - Duck Island and Sugar Island (Chase Osborn Preserve), 1947-1956 (Box 23)
      - Forest Properties Committee, 1952-1957 (Box 23)
      - Mud Lake, 1945-1965 (Box 23)
      - Newcomb Tract, 1932-1980 (Box 23)
      - Property Board, 1974-1983 (Box 23)
      - Proposed Work Plans, 1952/53-1958/59; 1965/66 (Box 23)
      - Ringwood Forest, 1956-1984 (Box 23)
      - Saginaw Forest, 1961-1984 (Box 23)
      - Stinchfield Woods, 1939-1986 (Box 23)
    - Reorganizations, 1972
      - Academic Programs Office (Box 23)
      - Faculty Recommendations (Box 23)
      - Graduate Affairs Office (Box 23)
      - Undergraduate Program (Box 23)
    - Research Committee, 1985 (Box 23)
    - Research Development Program
      - General, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Report, "Research Development Program: FY85 Accomplishments and FY86 Plans and Activities,", 1985 (Box 23)
      - Report, "Research Development Program: History, Status, Direction,", 1984 (Box 23)
      - Review by USDA Cooperative State Research Service, 1984-1985 (Box 23)
    - Residential Field Studies Curriculum, Task Force on, 1987 (Box 24)
    - Resource Ecology and Management
      - General, 1988/89-1989/90; 2 folders (Box 24)